A Guide to the Holmes Family Papers, 1721-1891
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Holmes Family Papers 1721-1891
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14748
The papers consist chiefly of family correspondence and also include poems, sermons, diaries, and genealogies, 1721-1891, ca. 1,000 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library Special Collections by Mr. and Mrs. Ralph J. Stoudt, Charlottesville, Virginia on July 15, 2009.
Scope and Content
The collection is a mixture of original material and handwritten or typed transcripts of earlier documents with explanatory notes.
The letters of Annamaria Pemberton Holmes chiefly convey family and social news, 1835-1837.
The journals of Charlotte Isabaella Holmes describe an extended stay in Le Havre and Dunkirk, France, 1849-1851, and family life in England, 1880. Her letters, 1853-1883, describe life in England.
The farm diary, 1861, of Edward Anderson Holmes, has a few scattered mentions of national events. His correspondence includes descriptions of surveying on Minnesota roads in the 1850s, land deals in Wisconsin, his Civil War service including essays and chronology about his capture in the third battle for Winchester, Va., with the 21st Virginia Cavalry, and imprisonment at Johnson's Island, Ohio. The collection also contains copies of poems, some original poems, lists of books read, personal and regimental accounts of provisions including fodder for horses and rations for prisoners, and lists of correspondents.
The collection also contains poems of Joseph Henry Hendon Holmes, 1816, and a note giving a horse to his daughter, 1819.
Letters of Maryanne Pemberton Holmes to Edward Anderson Holmes, 1852-1853, convey family and social news, and comment on life in the United States where sons Edward and George were living. The collection also includes miscellaneous writing by her including notes on property, an evening prayer, codicils to her will listing bequests, and brief diary entries on son Edward's schooling, 1838-1845. Of interest are her notes on Demerara [now Guyana], where her husband served as Judge Advocate General, including references to Doll Thomas, references to slaves both in general and in their employ, prices from account books, a translation of a South American Indian song, and lists of native plant and animal species, with two small sketches of a flamingo and a trumpeter bird. Also notes on her estate by R. T. Wilkinson, 1883-1884.
Letters to Sallie Campbell Starritt (Mrs. Edward Anderson) Holmes contain news of family and friends including a very brief reference to the breaking of the bank in Charlottesville, 1876, and a letter from her son Edward Buchanan Holmes, a student at the University of Virginia in 1890.
Papers of John and Mary Laurence include copies of their wills, 1731 and 1736
Papers of Elizabeth Pemberton, sister of Maryanne Pemberton Holmes, include letters describing a tour of the Lake district, 1819, and instructions regarding her property, together with her will, 1851.
Also of interest are prayers, poems and sermons of Dr. Stephen Pemberton and a series of letters to family discussing finances and theology.
Arrangement
The original organization of documents by family name has been retained.
Contents List
- Genealogies and Baptisms 1818 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Annamaria Pemberton Holmes: Will, Letters, and Diary 1835-1853 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Annamaria Pemberton Holmes: Will, Letters, and Diary 1837 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Charlotte Isabella Holmes: Letters, Diaries, and Poems 1849-1859 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Charlotte Isabella Holmes: Letters, Diaries, and Poems 1853-1883 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Edward Anderson Holmes: Diary (Box-folder 1:6)
- Edward Anderson Holmes: Poems, Letters, Letters to Ed (except Mother and Sisters), and Map of Durham with notations 1852-1888 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Edward Anderson Holmes: Poems, Letters, Letters to Ed (except Mother and Sisters), and Map of Durham with notations 1853-1891 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Edward Anderson Holmes: Civil War Years 1864-1865 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Edward Anderson Holmes: Civil War Years 1847-1865 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Letters, George Frederick Holmes to Charlotte Holmes, Robert Thomas Wilkinson to Charlotte Pemberton 1859-1889 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Joseph Henry Hendon Holmes: Poems and Gift n.d. (Box-folder 2:4)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Letters 1852-1853 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Letters 1852-1853 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Letters 1853 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Letters 1853 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Miscellaneous 1837-1859 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Miscellaneous 1846-1884 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Maryanne Pemberton Holmes: Notes on Demerara 1803-1836 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Letters to Sallie Campbell Starrett Holmes 1876-1893 (Box-folder 3:4)
- John and Mary Laurence: Documents, Newspaper Articles, and Wills 1721-1807 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Miscellany 1838-1844 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Elizabeth Pemberton: Letters, Poem, Will, Trip to the Lakes, and Funeral Instruction 1807-1851 (Box-folder 3:7)
- Stephen Pemberton: Alphabet and Prayers 1788 (Box-folder 3:8)
- Stephen Pemberton: Letters 1761-1766 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Stephen Pemberton: Poems 1766 (Box-folder 4:2)
- Stephen Pemberton: Poems 1768 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Stephen Pemberton: Poems 1769-1814 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Stephen Pemberton: Sermons 1755-1756 (Box-folder 4:5)
- Stephen Pemberton: Sermons 1766 (Box-folder 4:6)
- Stephen Pemberton: Sermons n.d. (Box-folder 4:7)
- Pictures Relative to Holmes and Related Families and Appendices n.d. (Box-folder 4:8)